ACWA's Rochester Joint Board Records 5619/043
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACWA's Rochester Joint Board Records
1922-1976
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Rochester Joint Board.
Sidney Hillman Foundation
5619/043
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Correspondence, reports, publications.
This collecion consists of correspondence, reports, collective bargaining agreements, and files from the Rochester Joint Board of Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Includes material related to the Sidney Hillman Foundation distinguished lecture series at the University of Rochester.
5566820
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
October 2010
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, March 2011
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related collections: 5273: ACWA's Rochester Joint Board Minutes of Meetings 5273 mf: ACWA's Rochester Joint Board Microfilm Minutes of Meetings 5285 mf: ACWA's Rochester Joint Board Microfilm Scrapbooks 5416 mf: ACWA's Rochester Joint Board and the Rochester Clothiers' Exchange Records 5619: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America 5619/043 AV: ACWA's Rochester Joint Board Audio-Visual Materials 5993 mf: ACWA's Rochester Joint Board Microfilm Minutes of Meetings And all other 5619 collections.
Arbitration, Industrial--New York (State)--Rochester.; Clothing workers--New York (State)--Rochester.; Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State)--Rochester.; Collective bargaining--Clothing industry--New York (State)--Rochester.; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Rochester Joint Board; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union --Archives; Sidney Hillman Foundation; Union of Needeltrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE) --Archives; UNITE HERE (Organization) --Archives
5566820
- Sidney Hillman Foundation. Distinguished lecturer series at University of Rochester., 1955-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Health Center plans., 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- General background of ACWA., 1922-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Background of ACWA in Rochester., 1939-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Memorandum of Law re Required Discharge of Union Employee (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Amalgamated Bank (1970) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Rochester Joint Board (RJB), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Political Material, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Community Projects, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- RJB notices and misc. correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Timely Clothes, Inc., 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Dues Increase Notices, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Robert Hall Clothes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- AFL-CIO Material, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Advance & Newspaper (Publicity & Correspondence), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Joint Board Correspondence, Other than Local, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- General Office Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Clothier's Exchange, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Bourjois, Inc., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bond Stores, Inc., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Box Plants, Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Amalgamated Bank (1972) (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Fashion Park, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Chatman, Arthur, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Fusing Material, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Comparative Stamp Sales, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Misc. Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- General Office, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Joint Board, Local, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Timely Clothes, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Syracuse and Utica Plants, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- State and Federal Mediation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Sheinkman, Jacob, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Rochester Clothiers Exchange, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Retail Stores, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Joint Board (Other than local), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Comparative Stamp Sales, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Amalgamated Insurance, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Bond Industries, Inc., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Boxes, Bravo, Bourjois & Buttons, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Political Material, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Research Dept., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Political Material [folder 1 of 2], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Political Material [folder 2 of 2], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Misc. correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Amalgamated Insurance Co., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Clothier's Exchange & Affiliates, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Firms not members of Clothier's Exchange: Box, Stores, Etc., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Community Projects, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Chatman, Abraham, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Bryan, William, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Bourjois, Inc., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Bond Stores, Inc, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Arbitration (Arthur Stark), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- New York State AFL-CIO etc., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Comparative Stamp Sales Reports, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- 27th Biennial Convention, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- General Office ACWA, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Material on Imports, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Joint Boards Not Local, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Metropolitan Thrift Store, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Political Material, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Research Dept, ACWA, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Job applicant correspondence and resumes, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Advance Editor, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Airlines Credit Slips, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Amalgamated Bank, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Amalgamated Insurance [folder 1 of 2], 1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Amalgamated Insurance [folder 2 of 2], 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Announcers, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Bond Clothes, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Christmas Card Order, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Comparison Stamp Sales & Report, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Community Projects, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Contract Re-opening Letters, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Contributions, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Correspondence and Thank yous, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Labor (State and Local), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- AFL-CIO Material, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- John Herling's Labor Letter, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Educational Material (Local and National), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- National Agreements, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Arbitration, notices and awards, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- General Office, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Research Material, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Rochester Button, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Amalgamated bank, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Cotton Garment, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Joseph & Feiss, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Labor Unity Newspaper, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Michaels Stern, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Joint Board notices, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Invitations and Telegrams, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- GEB Meeting, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- NYS Judicial Nominating Committee-Robert Millonzi [folder 1 of 3], 1976 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- NYS Judicial Nominating Committee-Robert Millonzi [folder 2 of 3], 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- NYS Judicial Nominating Committee-Robert Millonzi [folder 3 of 3], 1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Xerox Corp. Profit Sharing, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Convention Material, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Health Center, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- National Clothing, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Receipts, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Robert Hall, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Social Services, J. Miller, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Pavilion Nursing Home, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Xerox Corporation, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Tripp, HW Investments, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Xerox Profit Sharing, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous, 1959-1973 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Brand Name Directory (ACTWU members), 1989 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Agreements. Bond Stores, 1942-1971 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Agreements. Bond Stores, Sales People, 1952-1972 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Agreements. Bond Stores, Manufacturing, 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Agreements. Joseph Pietrafesca Co., Inc., 1963-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Agreements. Hickey-Freeman Co, 1965-1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Agreements. St. Joe Paper Co., 1962-1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Agreements. Timely Clothes, Inc., 1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Agreements. Sturdy Togs Inc, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Agreements. Robert Hall, 1965-1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Agreements. Rochester Button, 1953-1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Agreements. Rosco, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Agreements. Rubens Royal Uniform, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Agreements. Bourjois, Inc., 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Agreements. Duxback Corp, 1965-1969 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Agreements. Great Lakes Press, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Agreements. Joseph and Feiss Co, 1963-1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Agreements. Walter Jamieson Co, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Agreements. Metropolitan Thrift Center, 1964-1970 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Agreements. McFarlin Clothing Co, Retail Sales People, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Agreements. Michaels Stern & Co, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Agreements. National Clothing Co, Retails Sales People [folder 1 of 2], 1958-1966 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Agreements. National Clothing Co, Retails Sales People [folder 2 of 2], 1965-1971 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Agreements. National Suburban Stores, 1958-1968 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Agreements. Clothing Manufacturers Association., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Audit Examinations, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Established Rules between Clothiers' Exchange and RJB, 1945-1969 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Rates. Michaels Stern, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Rates. Pietrafesa, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 26)